<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-26T09:52:27-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Neighborhood Scale Software Patterns</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Public Fridge Stewardship</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/needs-protocol.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Public Fridge Stewardship" /><published>2021-02-20T03:47:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T03:47:00-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/needs-protocol</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/needs-protocol.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public fridges—with health departments often times looking the other way—have been popping up in New York City and throughout the country. A Freedge steward in Bushwick, states how “This is not charity; this is empowerment. There isn’t a group you have to thank. It’s something the community can own.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who is the “community” of the community fridge, and is what they’re stocking inside what they really want? How do you know if the food is old, discarded, and where did it come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open forum to log-in dates of when food was added, and who the current “stewards” are for maintenance protocols.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;social&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;food&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Productive Awkward Silences</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/productive-awkward-silences.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Productive Awkward Silences" /><published>2021-02-20T03:47:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T03:47:00-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/productive-awkward-silences</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/productive-awkward-silences.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Videoconferencing makes it possible to run group discussions that couldn’t happen before. However, they make group dynamics more complex, most notably deciding when to speak and when to remain silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower prevalence of body language, inability to create ad hoc side channels (such as whispering to one’s neighbor’s ear), shyness, wariness of micro-aggressions and many, many other factors can cause online classes and discussions involving strangers to devolve into uneasy silences. Organizers can be tempted to intervene every time nobody seems to be speaking, perhaps out of fear of an awkward moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letting the room stay silent for 20 to 30 seconds before an organizer intervenes enables better participation from everyone around.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;social&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;group dynamics&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Federated Decentralization</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/federated-decentralization.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Federated Decentralization" /><published>2021-02-20T02:33:27-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T02:33:27-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/federated-decentralization</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/20/federated-decentralization.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online life centralization enables corporate ownership and control of people’s data and means of expression. Complete decentralization and disintermediation, where every user owns and administrates their server nodes, is currently unfeasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online centralization is a well documented problem. It enables censorship and often prevents pro-active handling of trolling and moderation issues. Business owners’ interests rarely match the interests of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely decentralized networks, where each user is expected to run their own node for hosting or mining purposes, present a huge technical burden, and often require users to have spare machines, and uninterrupted internet access. More often than not, those systems encourage reintermediation, in the form of businesses that provide a better UI for transactions, enable discovery, store wallets or host servers. This defeats the purpose of decentralization and adds a chain of new intermediaries that need to be trusted, and whose interests might not match the user’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A federated network, where users connect to a specific node they choose. Each node is hosted and administered independently, and enforces its own rules. It is functionally the same as “intermediated decentralization” described above, but with the benefit of transparency. It does not pretend to be what it is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://joinmastodon.org&quot;&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt; fediverse.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://joinpeertube.org/&quot;&gt;PeerTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SMTP and email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;web&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;distributed&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Distraction Reclaimation</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/distraction-reclamation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Distraction Reclaimation" /><published>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/distraction-reclamation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/distraction-reclamation.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When transitioning from one task to another, or before attempting an emotionally draining activity, people tend to grab their phones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grabbing one’s phone as a form of fear avoidance or as a relief from anxiety often leads to… an increase of fear and anxiety. A person will often lose themselves in the infinite scroll of distracting content. Such behavior tends to be automatic and mindless, and often unsatisfying.
Multiple forces are in play: the need for emotional nourishment, the high availability of engaging yet unsatisfying content, the effort needed to compose and realign oneself, the instinctive nature of flicking phone screens, tapping apps and scrolling. In stressful situations, the marketplace of our attention rewards immediate satisfaction. This is the behavior that must be countered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 3 to 10 seconds delay before opening certain applications, leaving the person time to breathe and reflect on their reason for opening them in the first place. This delay is sufficient for the person to reclaim agency on their time, and resist switching their brain to automatic mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;beneficial-contexts&quot;&gt;Beneficial contexts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern could be applied whenever a significant context switch is to be experienced: before an important meeting, upon discovering a bug, when learning difficult news, when attempting to post a flaming reply to a bad tweet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;agency&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;attention&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context When transitioning from one task to another, or before attempting an emotionally draining activity, people tend to grab their phones. Problem Grabbing one’s phone as a form of fear avoidance or as a relief from anxiety often leads to… an increase of fear and anxiety. A person will often lose themselves in the infinite scroll of distracting content. Such behavior tends to be automatic and mindless, and often unsatisfying. Multiple forces are in play: the need for emotional nourishment, the high availability of engaging yet unsatisfying content, the effort needed to compose and realign oneself, the instinctive nature of flicking phone screens, tapping apps and scrolling. In stressful situations, the marketplace of our attention rewards immediate satisfaction. This is the behavior that must be countered. Solution A 3 to 10 seconds delay before opening certain applications, leaving the person time to breathe and reflect on their reason for opening them in the first place. This delay is sufficient for the person to reclaim agency on their time, and resist switching their brain to automatic mode. Beneficial contexts This pattern could be applied whenever a significant context switch is to be experienced: before an important meeting, upon discovering a bug, when learning difficult news, when attempting to post a flaming reply to a bad tweet.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Instant Redemption</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/instant-redemption.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Instant Redemption" /><published>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/instant-redemption</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/instant-redemption.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In groups, micro-agressions and other forms of invisible violence happen. They can take many forms: subtly caricaruting a group, imposing one’s authority, breaking boundaries, hurting people’s self-esteem. Often, those micro-agressions will be completely involuntary (or at least uncounsciously done).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When ignored, micro-agressions they can foster a very unhealthy environment and drive people to silence and isolation. Conversely, people’s susceptibilities to being called out for bad behavior make real talk about those issues incomfortable. As such, few people do the work of speaking out when they notice such things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social cues and conventions can make pointing out micro-agressions acceptable, as well as instantly apologizing for them.
For instance : A skit, played during the first day of a Recurse Center batch, shows a simple interaction: somebody saying something unthoughtful (“This is so easy, even my mother could use it”). Somebody else replies, automatically: “no subtle ageism and sexism!”. The first person says “Sorry!”. And the social interaction carries on. Presented as an example of “this is how people behave here”, it has a powerful effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;social&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;community&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;ritual&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context In groups, micro-agressions and other forms of invisible violence happen. They can take many forms: subtly caricaruting a group, imposing one’s authority, breaking boundaries, hurting people’s self-esteem. Often, those micro-agressions will be completely involuntary (or at least uncounsciously done).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neighborhood Message Board</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/neighborhood-message-board.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neighborhood Message Board" /><published>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/neighborhood-message-board</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/neighborhood-message-board.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small communities, often rural that find themselves at risk of natural dissaters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of overstressed emergency services, people need the ability to coordinate and share information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repsonding to the California wild fires, communities have set up informal fire watch and assistance groups. These often crop up on facebook. People keep tabs on fires, track possible dangerous conditions and organize efforts to help evacuate friends and neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;social&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;community&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context Small communities, often rural that find themselves at risk of natural dissaters</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Website Power Bar</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/website-powerbar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Website Power Bar" /><published>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/website-powerbar</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/website-powerbar.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You host a small server that is solar powered&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the battery runs out on a cloudy day. Users need a way to see how much time they have left to browse before the site goes offline&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a powerbar that surfaces the battery % to all users&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;remix&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;ui&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;solar&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context You host a small server that is solar powered Problem Sometimes the battery runs out on a cloudy day. Users need a way to see how much time they have left to browse before the site goes offline Solution Have a powerbar that surfaces the battery % to all users</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Algorithmic Transparency</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/algorithmic-transparency.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Algorithmic Transparency" /><published>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/algorithmic-transparency</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/algorithmic-transparency.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendation algorithms blackbox their internal logic and decision-making systems. We don’t know what kinds of data go in, and have no visibility into why certain decisions come out. We end up fetishising the algorithms and calling them “magic” to dismiss the need to make them legible to users&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendation algorithms on many popular social media platforms run unchecked – as an audience we have no visibility into what metrics the engineers are optimising for. The engineers themselves don’t fully understand how the algorithms choose what to recommend. The lack of transparency makes it difficult to evaluate why we’re being shown certain content. It hides the fact some algorithms maximise for qualities like emotional outrage, shock value, and political extremism. We lack the agency to evaluate and change the algorithms serving us content.
These algorithms also decide what advertisements we see based on the data the platform has access to. As users we have no way of understanding what data is being used, and why certain companies or products are targeting us as potential customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a piece of content is recommended by an automated system, it should include an epistemic disclosure message explaining why it was suggested, and what factors went into that decision.
Advertisements in particular should bear these disclosures, indicating what data points led to the ad being served (age, gender, race, location, income)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;algorithms&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;transparency&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context Recommendation algorithms blackbox their internal logic and decision-making systems. We don’t know what kinds of data go in, and have no visibility into why certain decisions come out. We end up fetishising the algorithms and calling them “magic” to dismiss the need to make them legible to users Problem Recommendation algorithms on many popular social media platforms run unchecked – as an audience we have no visibility into what metrics the engineers are optimising for. The engineers themselves don’t fully understand how the algorithms choose what to recommend. The lack of transparency makes it difficult to evaluate why we’re being shown certain content. It hides the fact some algorithms maximise for qualities like emotional outrage, shock value, and political extremism. We lack the agency to evaluate and change the algorithms serving us content. These algorithms also decide what advertisements we see based on the data the platform has access to. As users we have no way of understanding what data is being used, and why certain companies or products are targeting us as potential customers. Solution When a piece of content is recommended by an automated system, it should include an epistemic disclosure message explaining why it was suggested, and what factors went into that decision. Advertisements in particular should bear these disclosures, indicating what data points led to the ad being served (age, gender, race, location, income)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Algorithmic Agency &amp;amp; BYO Algorithms</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/byo-algorithms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Algorithmic Agency &amp;amp; BYO Algorithms" /><published>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/byo-algorithms</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/byo-algorithms.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of web platforms we spend time on use private algorithms to decide what content we see. As users we have very minimal control over the data that is fed into these algorithms, how they make desicions, and what varibles they optimise for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of agency users have in the algorithimic decision making process creates a large power discrepancy. We have to accept whatever the algorithm serves up if we want to use the platform. There are very few affordances in the user interface design of these platforms that allow us to adjust the algorithm to serve our personal values and interests, as opposed tot he values and interests of the platform owners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Provide affordances in the user interface that let people customise and tweak the programmes that generate algorithmically provided content. On a shallow level this might be indicating we like or dislike a certain piece of content, or want to see more content related to it. On a more meaningful level we would be able to adjust the input variables of these algorithms, adjust the outcomes they optimising for, and tailor them to our personal values and goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;algorithms&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;transparency&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context The majority of web platforms we spend time on use private algorithms to decide what content we see. As users we have very minimal control over the data that is fed into these algorithms, how they make desicions, and what varibles they optimise for. Problem The lack of agency users have in the algorithimic decision making process creates a large power discrepancy. We have to accept whatever the algorithm serves up if we want to use the platform. There are very few affordances in the user interface design of these platforms that allow us to adjust the algorithm to serve our personal values and interests, as opposed tot he values and interests of the platform owners. Solution Provide affordances in the user interface that let people customise and tweak the programmes that generate algorithmically provided content. On a shallow level this might be indicating we like or dislike a certain piece of content, or want to see more content related to it. On a more meaningful level we would be able to adjust the input variables of these algorithms, adjust the outcomes they optimising for, and tailor them to our personal values and goals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Community Driven Documentation</title><link href="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/community-driven-documentation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Community Driven Documentation" /><published>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T23:38:15-08:00</updated><id>/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/community-driven-documentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/neighborhood-scale-software-patterns/pattern/2021/02/12/community-driven-documentation.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emerging products or platforms that have a non-trivial learning curve, and are built by small teams with limited resources and bandwidth. Combined with a user base of highly-engaged early adopters who feel a strong affinity for the new platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The creators of the product are often in the worst position to explain it others – they lack beginners mind, and know too much about its inner workings and messy details. Documentation and onboarding experiences are often low on the priority list and go neglected. If they do exist, they’re incomplete, unhelpful, or actively confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The creators purposefully write minimal or incomplete documentation. In the absence of “official” instructions on how to use the system, early adopters write blog posts, make tutorial videos, and exchange advice on social media platforms with one another.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="pattern" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;stewardship&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;maintenance&quot;}" /><category term="{&quot;tag&quot;=&gt;&quot;community&quot;}" /><summary type="html">Context Emerging products or platforms that have a non-trivial learning curve, and are built by small teams with limited resources and bandwidth. Combined with a user base of highly-engaged early adopters who feel a strong affinity for the new platform. Problem The creators of the product are often in the worst position to explain it others – they lack beginners mind, and know too much about its inner workings and messy details. Documentation and onboarding experiences are often low on the priority list and go neglected. If they do exist, they’re incomplete, unhelpful, or actively confusing. Solution The creators purposefully write minimal or incomplete documentation. In the absence of “official” instructions on how to use the system, early adopters write blog posts, make tutorial videos, and exchange advice on social media platforms with one another.</summary></entry></feed>